<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Short and plain directions for the observation of the Lords day as they were delivered in a sermon in the church of Mallow, in the diocess of Cloyne : suited to the capacity of the common people / by John Bulkelly, M.A. and rector of Cloyne.</title>
            <author>Bulkelly, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77773</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5402</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42873</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">38875878</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 38875878</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152230</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77773)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152230)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2286:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Short and plain directions for the observation of the Lords day as they were delivered in a sermon in the church of Mallow, in the diocess of Cloyne : suited to the capacity of the common people / by John Bulkelly, M.A. and rector of Cloyne.</title>
                  <author>Bulkelly, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 13 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Jos. Ray ... for William Norman ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Lambeth Palace Library (London, England).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sunday --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152230:1"/>
            <p>SHORT AND PLAIN DIRECTIONS FOR THE OBSERVATION OF THE LORDS DAY; As they were delivered in a SERMON IN THE CHURCH of <hi>MALLOW</hi> in the Dioceſs of CLOYNE.</p>
            <p>Suited to the Capacity of the Common People.</p>
            <p>By JOHN BULKELLY, M. A and Rector of <hi>Mallow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BLIN:</hi> Printed by <hi>Joſ. Ray</hi> in <hi>Eſſex ſtreet,</hi> for <hi>William Norman</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Dames ſtreet,</hi> 1697.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:152230:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152230:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To my Well-Beloved the</hi> Pariſhioners <hi>and</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants <hi>of</hi> Mallow.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dearly Beloved,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AS the whole deſign of penning the enſuing Diſcourſe was for your advantage, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting the Service of God in that Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which he hath called Me to the Cure of: So the publication of the ſame, (without any ſiniſter or by end of Credit, or Profit to my ſelf) tends on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to your uſe and edification, that what was once tranſiently delivered, and (therefore according to that ſaying) might ſlip in at one Ear and out at the other, and ſo be eaſily forgotten, may be now pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to your conſtant view, and accordingly to your meditation and ſtudy. Thence it is that I aim at no other Patron but your ſelves, nor will I apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logize for my Stile or Language, which the plainer it is, it ſo much the better fits a mixt auditory. I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign not the delight or encomiums of ſome, but the benefit of all, and therefore hope the ſenſe will be
<pb facs="tcp:152230:3"/>attended to more than the words. The wiſeſt of Men tells us, <hi>Prov.</hi> 11.30. <hi>That he that winneth Souls is wiſe, (i.e.)</hi> that he that perſwades is the beſt Orator. So that if this Diſcourſe hath its intended effects up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your Lives and Converſations, I fear no critical remark and cenſures, but have my end in being dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent in my Miniſtry, and ſhewing my ſelf in every thing, but eſpecially in relation to your Souls and Spiritual Concerns.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt faithful and affectionate Servant <hi>J. B.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:152230:3"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> ſhall ſpeak a little concerning the <hi>change of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath,</hi> from <hi>the laſt</hi> to <hi>the firſt Day of the Week,</hi> and then refer you to the following Diſcourſe for the ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification thereof.</p>
            <p>God, the Almighty Architect, no ſooner finiſhed his Work, in which he took up <hi>ſix days,</hi> but he proclaimed a <hi>Reſt</hi> on the <hi>ſeventh:</hi> Which <hi>Reſt</hi> ſignifies, Firſt a <hi>Temporal one;</hi> that Man having ſpent <hi>ſix days</hi> in his own Employment, in making proviſion for Himſelf and Family, was on the <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day</hi> obliged, by Divine Inſtitution, to muſter up all the faculties of his Soul, and then to imploy them in the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular and moſt ſpiritual worſhip of God his Creator.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It ſignifies a <hi>Spiritual Reſt,</hi> a Reſt from the drudgery of ſin, and that mean and ſlaviſh work which the Devil, our grievous Task-maſter, exacts of us.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, It ſignifies an <hi>Eternal Reſt</hi> in Heaven, of the ſpirits of juſt men made perfect, where <hi>they reſt from their labors,</hi> from all the Troubles and Calamities of this World, in the enjoyment of the ever bleſſed God in the boſom of their Saviour.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:152230:4"/>
            <p>But it is only the <hi>Temporal Sabbath</hi> that I treat of, which, with good ground, and upon good authority, is changed from the <hi>laſt</hi> to the <hi>firſt day</hi> of the Week, from <hi>Saturday</hi> to <hi>Sunday,</hi> now commonly known by the name of the <hi>Lords Day;</hi> becauſe it was that day of the Week on which the great Saviour of the World roſe from the dead: In memory of which, and in a grateful acknowledgment of the great mercy of our Redemption, fully compleated by his Reſurrection, the <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath</hi> which was ſolemnized on the <hi>laſt,</hi> hath been tranſlated to the <hi>firſt day of the Week,</hi> and accordingly ſince our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours time, hath been celebrated in all Chriſtian Churches throughout the World: Mark then, that as the <hi>Jewiſh Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath</hi> was ſanctified becauſe of the finiſhing of <hi>the work of Creation,</hi> ſo was the <hi>Chriſtian Sabbath</hi> becauſe of the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing of <hi>the work of Redemption,</hi> which is of far greater importance, (Man by it being born again with more wonder than he was firſt made) and therefore deſerves more to be celebrated than the other. This then being <hi>a day</hi> that the Lord hath made for himſelf, therefore <hi>let us be glad and rejoice therein.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Vale.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152230:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Short and Plain Directions for the Obſervation of the</hi> Lords Day, <hi>as they were delivered in a</hi> Sermon, &amp;c.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Exodus XX. Verſ. 8.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Remember the Sabbath Day to keep it holy.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE ſanctification of this day conſiſteth in a holy Reſt, and the performance of holy Duties, as appears by the ninth Verſe, <hi>Six days ſhalt thou labour and do all thy work;</hi> but the tenth Verſe proclaims a Reſt, a Ceſſation from all Work; <hi>But the ſeventh day is the Sabbath of the Lord thy God: in it thou ſhalt do no manner of work.</hi> And this Reſt may be termed, a prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion unto the ſanctification of this day, as a remedy againſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction, becauſe unleſs we reſt we cannot ſanctifie. The ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication therefore of this day, with the duties to be performed therein, belonging either to the Paſtor or to the People: The whole Congregation will come under that diviſion as to the publick ſanctification of this day: The Paſtors, or Miniſters, are to be chief actors in the publick ſanctification of the Sabbath; but it is not neceſſary at this time to treat of their duty.</p>
            <p>Becauſe I ſpeak to Laymen, who deſire rather (I ſuppoſe) to hear of their own duty, than be inquiſitive after the duty of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. As alſo,</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:152230:5"/>
            <p>Becauſe every man now adays doth take upon him to teach <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e Miniſter his duty, even he that will be ranged in no duty himſelf. And laſtly, Becauſe</p>
            <p>Paſtors and People being Relatives; the duty of the one will in a great meaſure appear by the explication of the duty of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>The conſecration then of the Sabbath's reſt conſiſts in perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing three ſorts of Duties <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rſt. Before. 2dly. At. 3dly. After the publick exerciſe of the Church.</p>
            <p>The Duties to be performed before the publick Servics are.</p>
            <p>Firſt, To riſe up early, to prepare our ſelves, as alſo to conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate as much of the Lords day unto the Lords ſervice and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip as may be. Of the Prophets the Lord ſaith, <hi>Jer.</hi> 7.25. <hi>I have ſent unto you all my ſervants the Prophets, daily riſing up early and ſending them.</hi> Our Saviour (<hi>Mark</hi> 1.) in the morning before day aroſe and prayed ſo long, and came into the Synagogue, which may be concluded to be on the Sabbath, by comparing the 35th. Verſ. with the 38th, and 39th. And thoſe devout Women, <hi>Luk,</hi> 24. <hi>upon the firſt day of the week, very early in the morning, came to the Sepulchre</hi> to ſeek their Saviour. Let theſe Examples induce us not to miſpend any part of this day, but to riſe ſooner on this day than on other days, by how much the ſervice of God is to be preferred before all earthly buſineſs; for there is no Maſter to ſerve ſo good as God, and in the end no work ſhall be better rewarded than his ſervice.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Let us examine our Conſciences, and confeſs our Sins to God, and renew our Vows, to walk more conſcionably, that we may bring into the preſence of God, and his Aſſembly, (being that of Saints) the peace of a quiet heart.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, We muſt join with our Families in private Prayer, or if our ſtate and condition be not ſuch, yet by our ſelves to pray ſervently to God. 1ſt. Both for our ſelves, that we may be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable Hearers, for Underſtanding, Memory, Grace, and a Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing on the Word. 2dly. As alſo for our Teachers and Inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, that God would give them utterance, that they may ſpeak boldly as they ought to ſpeak in the demonſtration of the Spirit
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152230:5"/>and of Power; and that God would direct their hearts to medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate upon ſuch Truths as may be wholeſom and ſeaſonable for our preſent condition; either for Correction or Comfort, as our caſe moſt requireth: That he would whet the Miniſters Tongue, to how down all ſuperfluity and naughtineſs in us, and ſpeak ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that may kill our Sin and create the fruit of peace on his Lips to comfort our wounded Conſciences. When we have thus pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared our hearts to ſeek and ſerve the Lord, let us get betimes to Church, before the beginning of publick Exerciſes, that we may joyn therein with the Congregation of the Faithful. We read in <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 46.10. That the Prince was to make as much haſte to the Temple as the meaneſt in the Congregation. He was to go in, <hi>in the midſt of them.</hi> The people waited for <hi>Zacharias, Luke</hi> 1. The Diſciples at <hi>Treas</hi> came together to hear <hi>Paul</hi> preach, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.7. At <hi>Antioch</hi> the whole City almoſt were come <hi>together to hear the word of God, Act.</hi> 13.44. And <hi>Cornelius</hi> and his company ſaid unto <hi>Peter, we are all here preſent before God, to hear all things that are Commanded thee of God, Acts</hi> 10.33. As we are going to Church, let us meditate with our ſelves that we are going to the Court of the Lord, to ſpeak with our great God by Prayer, and to hear his Majeſty ſpeak unto us by his Word, and to receive his bleſſing on our Souls.</p>
            <p>When we enter into the Church let the Majeſty of the place, and the preſence there, affect our hearts with a holy zeal and aw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful reverence. <hi>Quis locus eſt Templis anguſtior?</hi> ſaith the Poet. What place more auguſt and noble, more honourable and ſtately, than the Temples dedicated to the worſhip and ſervice of God? Let us conſider that this is none other but the Houſe of God; the Gate of Heaven where God is in an eſpecial manner preſent with his holy Angels. And therefore let us not omit to worſhip kneeling down, or bowing the head, or proſtrating the whole body; worſhip the Lord at his footſtool, <hi>O come let us worſhip and fall down and kneel before the Lord our Maker.</hi> Whether to the <hi>Eaſt</hi> or to the <hi>Weſt</hi> is not material, the Scripture determines no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in that particular. Every Church in things indifferent may eſtabliſh ſuch Rites as in wiſdom ſhall be thought moſt convenient
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152230:6"/>for the preſervation of unity and uniformity in God's worſhip. True it is that the antient Fathers in the primitive Church did generally worſhip towards the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> and lay down the grounds or reaſons of that cuſtom: and the Heathens accuſed the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans becauſe they worſhip'd God towards the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> that they did worſhip the <hi>Sun</hi> (as <hi>Tertullian</hi> relates in his Apolegiticks) as now alſo ſome too uncharitably charge thoſe among us that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the like cuſtom, as if they worſhip the <hi>Communion Table.</hi> This practice of the Ancients ſerves to wipe off the imputation of Popery from theſe. Yet it is but an indifferent Rite or Ceremony, and the diſuſance thereof not to be condemned in any, while the Church hath not eſtabliſhed it. Chriſtians have no ſuch command from God in Scripture. 'Tis certain God will hear their prayers that worſhip him, whither they turn their faces towards the Bell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fry or towards the Chancell.</p>
            <p>Being thus ready and prepared for the publick ſolemn ſervice, which begins with Prayer by a Miniſter lawfully call'd and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rized thereunto. Gods Houſe is emphatically called the Houſe of Prayer by our Saviour; <hi>When thy People ſhall make ſupplication unto thee in this Houſe,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon; Then hear thou in Heaven thy dwelling place, and when thou heareſt forgive.</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> exhorts, <hi>that</hi> in the Churches <hi>firſt of all Supplications, Prayers, Interceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and giving of thanks, be made for all men,</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.1. The Apoſtles <hi>continued with one accord in Prayer and Supplications, Act.</hi> 1.14. And the Church aſſembled at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is ſaid to have continued ſtedfaſtly in the Apoſtles Doctrine and Fellowſhip, and in breaking of Bread and in Prayers. Prayers are every where acknowledged by the Fathers as a neceſſary part of the publick ſervice, requiſite to the ſanctification of this day: Not only Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture was read, <hi>Sèd etiám Petitiones erant delegatae,</hi> ſaith <hi>Tertull.</hi> But alſo Prayers were delegated or ſent up to God. <hi>Ad Deum quaſi manufactâ precationibus ambiamus orantes;</hi> Which <hi>Zanchy</hi> well explaineth thus; Let us go unto God with our joynt prayers, as with a ſpiritual Army, or Volly of Shot, offering humble violence to the Throne of Grace.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:152230:6"/>
            <p>Now concerning theſe prayers three things are obſervable. 1ſt. That they were made in a known Tongue, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.15, 16. every nation in their own vulgar Language prayed, and God, who is Lord of all Tongues, hears every one praying in his own Tongue; and their ſeveral Languages craving the ſame things juſt and honeſt, and ſutable to his will, make a ſweet conſort, a melodious harmony in the Ears of God, 2dly. Theſe Prayers muſt be directed to God alone, in and thrô Jeſus Chriſt; He is the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer of Prayers. The Primitive Chriſtians were ſenſible that they could not obtain from any other what they prayed for, therefore they made their addreſs to God alone in their prayers, becauſe he alone was able to perform their requeſt: What extream folly and ignorance is it to offer ſuch ſupplications as are proper only to God, unto thoſe who are no Gods. 3dly. Let us inquire whether theſe prayers muſt needs be <hi>extempore,</hi> without premeditation, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they may not be a ſet Form, or Liturgy, compoſed by the Church and commanded to be uſed.</p>
            <p>In ancient time the people of God were in ſpecial neceſſity directed to pray in a ſet form, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14.2. <hi>Take with you words,</hi> &amp;c. (i. e.) Take ſuch words as are convenient for the expreſſing of that which I tell you is neceſſary for you in this miſerable condition that you are in; take words that have been ſeriouſly weighed and made fit for you, take ſuch words as I preſcribe unto you, as I direct, as I dictate, take theſe very words and ſay, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This was no novelty to the people of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> they had preſcribed unto them a ſet form of Confeſſion at their offering of the firſt Fruits, and of Prayer, for him that offered the third years Tythes, <hi>Deut.</hi> 26.</p>
            <p>Moſes uſed a ſet form of words at the raiſing and ſetting of the Ark, <hi>Numb.</hi> 10.35. <hi>Aaron</hi> was directed in a ſet form of words to bleſs the people, <hi>Num.</hi> 6. And there was a ſet form of Curſes. <hi>Deut</hi> 27. <hi>Moſes</hi>'s ſong was written for a Hymn for after times. And what are <hi>David</hi>'s <hi>Pſalms</hi> but ſet forms of Prayer, Petitions, thankſgivings for Benefits, and deprecations againſt Evil. Our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour in the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> preſcribed a Form of Prayer to his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, as St. <hi>John the Baptiſt</hi> his immediate fore-runner had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly done to his Diſciples. St. <hi>Paul</hi> often uſed the ſame ſet form
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152230:7"/>of Prayer without variation. Our Saviour had a better gift in praying than any man in the world, and could have varied his words better than any other, yet when he had the ſame ſuit to make to his Father, he uſed the ſame words diverſe times, ſaying once again, and yet a third time, <hi>Father, if it be poſſible let this Cup paſs from me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Primitive times I doubt not but they did pray and preach too, as the Spirit gave them utterance, but when that immediate aſſiſtance of the Spirit ceaſed, they ſaw the inconvenience of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temporary Prayers, and were enforced to compile publick Forms or Liturgies; for as St. <hi>Aug.</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Quidam in precibus loquti ſunt contrà Regulam Fidei,</hi> Some in their prayers ſpeak diſſonant to the Rule of Faith. Some prayed Hereſy, ſome Schiſme, and ſome Blaſphemy: In remedy whereof the Council of <hi>Laodicaea</hi> decreed that it ſhould not be lawful for any to frame ſet forms of Prayer at their pleaſure, and recite them in their publick Aſſemblies; But the accuſtomed prayers which had been approved ſhould be uſed in every meeting. And the Councel of <hi>Carthage</hi> decreed that what prayers ſoever a man framed for himſelf he ſhould firſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint thoſe that were wiſe and learned with them, before he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed to uſe them, and alſo decreed that <hi>Nullae aliae preces vel Orationes dicerentur in Eccleſia, niſi quae à ſynodo erant approbatae;</hi> that no other prayer or ſupplications be uſed in the Church but ſuch as are approved by a Synod: And the reaſon is given, <hi>nè forte aliquid contra fidem vel per Ignorantiam, vel per minus ſtudium ſit Compoſitum;</hi> Leaſt by ſudden extemporary effuſion of prayer, without good advice and meditation, ſome expreſſions might ſlip from him, either through Ignorance or Careleſneſs, which were not conſonant to the Faith of Chriſt's Church, no nor beſeeming the awful Majeſty of Almighty God. And now I appeal to your Conſciences whether the ſame neceſſity doth not lie on us to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Publick Liturgie or Service Book from contempt and diſuſance, ſeing ſo many different <hi>Sects</hi> and <hi>dangerous Hereſies</hi> are crept in among us, as <hi>Presbyterians, Independants, Anabaptiſts, Seek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> &amp;c. whoſe prayers if they be true to their own Poſitions cannot be conſonant to the rule of Faith; and conſequently we cannot
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152230:7"/>with a good Conſcience ſay <hi>Amen</hi> thereunto. I cloſe up this with the ſpeech of <hi>Polycarpus, O Deus in quae tempora reſervaſti nos?</hi> O God for what times haſt thou reſerved us? wherein that ſervice of thine which hath heretofore had the high approbation, applauſe and commendation of many learned Divines, and glorious Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, is now expoſed to the careleſs neglect, to the proud contempt and ſcorn of new fangled diſaffected perſons, and villifyed as po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh and ſuperſtitious; whoſe particular exceptions againſt it, or any paſſage in it, have received full, particular, and abundant ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction by the Learned pens of <hi>Hooker, Fiſher, Falkner,</hi> and of Dr. <hi>King</hi> the now Biſhop of <hi>Derry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I now come to the peoples Duty at the time of publick ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, when prayers are beginning; lay aſide thine own private meditations. Let thy heart joyn with the Miniſter and the whole Church, as being one Body of Chriſt, and becauſe God is the God of Order, he will have all things to be done in the Church with one heart, and one agreement; The exerciſes of the Church are common and publick, no body is excluded from it's harmony, <hi>vis unita fortior.</hi> It is an ignorant pride for a man to think his own private prayers more effectual than the publick prayers of the whole Church; pray therefore when the Church prayeth; ſing when they ſing; and let thy heart and affection be intent upon, and run along with the publick prayers; let not thy heart be roving while thy tongue is at prayer. 2dly. Let thy behaviour at prayer be ſuch as becometh Saints; the ordinary poſtures at prayer were ſtanding, kneeling, or lying along upon the ground; but the uſual poſture was kneeling: <hi>Euſebius</hi> witneſſeth that the Chriſtian Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers kneeled in their prayers: <hi>Arnobius</hi> affirms that Chriſtians when they ador'd God with their joynt prayers, did uſe proſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The Church commandeth prayers to be made with all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence and genuflection on the ſet or appointed days. True it is, that for joy of our Saviours Reſurrection, the ancient Church would not kneel in her prayers, between <hi>Eaſter</hi> and <hi>Whitſuntide</hi> as we read in <hi>Tertull,</hi> and <hi>Juſt. Mart.</hi> and when that Ceremony was omitted in ſome places, the 20th Can: of the firſt Councel of <hi>Nice</hi> decreed, that it ſhould be obſerved in every place, yet
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152230:8"/>we find in <hi>Acts</hi> 21.5. that St. <hi>Paul</hi> prayed with bended knees on the ſhore of <hi>Tyre,</hi> between the Feaſt of <hi>Paſcha,</hi> and <hi>Pentecoſt.</hi> Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the days of Unleavened Bread he ſayled from <hi>Philippi</hi> and haſtned to be at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the day of <hi>Pentecoſt,</hi> and paſſing thrô <hi>Tyre</hi> in this his journy towards <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> he kneeled down on the ſhore and prayed, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.6.16. Kneeling then is the moſt ſeemly geſture in prayer, but if thou canſt not thrô ſome bodily infirmity, or for want of room, why then ſtand. But ſitting is a moſt irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verent and unſeemly geſture at prayer time. When thou prayeſt thou askeſt a Bleſſing, and doſt it upon thy knees; if to thy earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father how much more to thy heavenly. But men have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted the courſe now, they drink their health upon their knees, and pray for their health upon their tayles; God ſhall anſwer ſuch men according to their manners. Laſtly, at the cloſe of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry prayer ſay <hi>Amen. Neh.</hi> 8.6. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.16. So did the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Chriſtians, <hi>ad ſimilitudinem caeleſtis tonitru Amen reboabat</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Hierom.</hi> The whole Congregation reſoundeth <hi>Amen</hi> like a crack of Thunder, till the Church did ring again After prayer ſucceedeth the publick reading of the Word, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.10. where it appears that the end of our gathering is to hear the word that is ſanctified for ſanctification. <hi>Moſes</hi> was read among the Jews, in their Synagogue, upon that Sabbath day, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.21. Among Chriſtians alſo <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets were read at firſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.15. Then the Goſpels, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.18. We have ſent with <hi>Titus,</hi> the Brother whoſe praiſe is in the Goſpel throughout all the Churches; whence we may not improbably gather that the Goſpel of St. <hi>Luke</hi> was read in all the Churches in Sr. <hi>Paul</hi>'s time. St. <hi>Paul</hi> chargeth the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> that the Epiſtle ſent unto them be read unto all the holy Brethren; and he deſires of the <hi>Colloſſians</hi> that they would read the Epiſtle written from <hi>Laodicaea,</hi> and cauſe that which was ſent unto them to be read to the <hi>Laodiceans.</hi> After the death of the Apoſtles; their writings alſo were read in the publick Congregation, as the Fathers of the Church do witneſs: While the word is audibly and diſtinctly read you muſt liſten at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentively thereunto, and with ſubmiſſion yield your ſelves to be governed and directed thereby: But reading of the word is not
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152230:8"/>all that is required of the Miniſter, but if he will ſanctify this day he muſt preach: Under the Law, <hi>Moſes</hi> of old time had in every City them that preacht him, being read in the Synagogue every Sabbath day. <hi>Acts</hi> 15.21. For it was the manner of the Jews to read a piece of the <hi>Pentateuch</hi> every Sabbath, and being diſtinctly read, one of the elder Levites did interpret and expound it unto the People, as you may read <hi>Neh</hi> 8.4.7, 8. This Cuſtom <hi>Philo Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daeus</hi> mentions, who was contemporary with the Apoſtles: when the Prieſt, or one of the Elders, had read ſome part of the Law; ſaith he, <hi>ſigillatim exponit,</hi> he expoundeth it particularly: And what are the writings of the Prophets but the abridgments or ſummary heads of their Sermons. Our bleſſed Saviour when he read his Text cloſed the Book and made application to the People; he proved from his Text that he was to preach the Goſpel, to preach Deliverance, to preach the acceptable year of the Lord.</p>
            <p>In the primitive Church, after the writings of the Apoſtles and Prophets were read, the Preſident or Chief Miniſter, made a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, wherein he inſtructed the People, and exhorted them to the practice of thoſe Dutys then taught and delivered. When the Miniſter calls upon thee to hear Gods word, and read his Text, ſtand up, <hi>Neh.</hi> 8.5. When <hi>Ehud</hi> pretended a ſecret errand from God unto the King, <hi>Eglon</hi> roſe out of his ſeat, <hi>Judges,</hi> 3. While the Preacher is expounding and applying the word of the Lord, look upon him, for it is a great help to ſtir up thine attention, and to keep thee from wandring thoughts. So the eyes of all that were in the Synagogue are ſaid to have been faſtned on Chriſt whileſt he preached, and all the people hanged upon him when they heard him, chaſing away all wandring thoughts, omitting reading, praying, or being otherwiſe employed: And laſtly, forbearing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference or drowſineſs, liſten with all readineſs and attention, ſix in thy memory the coherence and connexion of the Text, with what went before, the diviſion of it into its ſeveral parts, and the main doctrines or points of Inſtruction, the proofs that ratify the truth and certainty of the Doctrine, the reaſons that evince it, and the uſes or applycation thereof for the benefit of thine own
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152230:9"/>Soul. If thou canſt not comprehend all theſe, mark dilligently the Doctrine and uſes, let not theſe ſlip thy careful Obſervation.</p>
            <p>When the <hi>Sermon</hi> is ended, beware thou depart not, like the nine Lepers, till that for thine Inſtruction to ſaving health, thou haſt returned thanks, and praiſes to God, by an after prayer and ſinging of a Pſalm. St. <hi>Aug.</hi> accounteth it <hi>totum opus Sabbathi,</hi> as if the Sabbath was made for nothing elſe but only for thankſgiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and prayers, <hi>David</hi> deſireth Deliverance, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 35.18. and promiſeth that being heard, he will ſing his praiſe in the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Of ſinging Pſalms in the Church the Apoſtle ſpeaks, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.26. For ſinging of Pſalms to God we have both the precept, and the example, of our Lord and his Apoſtles, and the Enemies of Chriſtianity (in the Infancy of the Goſpel) acknowledg that the Chriſtians had their meeting before break of Day, to ſing unto Chriſt and unto God; <hi>Lucian Philopater.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the <hi>Bleſſing</hi> is pronounced ſtand up or kneel, to receive thy part therein, and hear it as if Chriſt himſelf, whoſe Miniſter he is) did pronounce the ſame unto thee, and by no means de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part without the Bleſſing. The Prince was not to go forth out of the Temple till the whole Congregation went forth; he had no privilidge to depart thence more then the meaneſt in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, till the ſolemn ſervice was ended. When <hi>Solomon</hi> in the dedication of the Temple, had made an end of praying all his prayer, 1. <hi>King.</hi> 8.54. they went not out but ſtayed for the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. In the primitive times, he that ſhould go out of the Church before Sermon were ended, was liable to Eccleſiaſtical cenſure: What good will the Service or Sermon do thee, if thou want the Bleſſing.</p>
            <p>When the <hi>Bleſſing</hi> is pronounced, adore bowing thy Head, or bending thy Knee, with ſome ſhort ejaculatory prayer and thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving to God, and ſo either depart with reverence, or proceed to the celebration of the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> if it be that day admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:152230:9"/>
            <p>Turn not thy back upon the <hi>Lords Ordinance;</hi> refuſe not to come when invited to his <hi>Table.</hi> It is one thing not to receive often, by reaſon it is not the cuſtom of that Church wherein thou li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt to adminiſter often; and another thing to refuſe to come, though invited, and to turn thy back upon thoſe dainties, when prepared. What preparation we muſt make to receive with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, and what are the pleas which hinder us, in this Duty, I ſhall e're long declare unto you, and then endeavour with the beſt skill I can to remove all thoſe pleas and hinderances: in the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rim be admoniſhed in the action of kneeling, ſtanding, ſitting, and ſuch indifferent ceremonies; for the avoiding of ſcandal, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of charity, and in teſtimony of thine obedience, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form thy ſelf to the manner of the Church, wherein thou liveſt. When I come to <hi>Rome</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi>) I faſt on the Sabbath; when I am here, I do not faſt; ſo do thou, unto whatſoever Church thou chance to come, obſerve the Rites and Cuſtoms thereof, if thou wouldſt neither give nor take offence.</p>
            <p>Alſo remember always to be preſent at the <hi>Baptiſm of Infants,</hi> 1ſt. That thou mayeſt omit no part of Publick Worſhip of God, but pray with the Church and Congregation (2dly) That thou mayeſt outwardly grace God's Ordinance, and countenance it, (as it were) with thy preſence, and not diſgrace or ſeem to ſcorn it, by turning thy back unto it. (3dly) That God's publick Ordinance may be publickly, and not privately performed, and that thou mayeſt aſſiſt the Church in praiſing God, for grafting another Member into his Myſtical Body. (4thly) That thou mayeſt ſhew thy ſelf to be a Freeman of Chriſts Corporation, having a voyce or conſent in the admiſſion of others into that holy Society. (5thly) That thou mayeſt repay thy debts, in praying for that Infant, which is to be Baptiz'd, (as other Chriſtians did in the like caſe for thee) that God would give him the new effects of Baptiſm, by his Blood and Spirit. (6thly) That alſo thou mayeſt hereby call to mind thy Covenant with God in Baptiſm, and Gods Covenant made with thee, and examine what fruit thereof appears within
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152230:10"/>thee, that thou mayeſt bleſs God, if thou find the ſame effectual, and be humbled to labour unto it, if thou find it to be ſmall.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Remember to caſt thy mite into the <hi>poor mans Box, Deut.</hi> 16.16. There is a charge to <hi>Aaron,</hi> that whenſoever they came to appear before the Lord, none of them ſhould appear emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty handed. <hi>Lev.</hi> 8.31. There is mention made of a Basket of ſanctification, in which were reſerved thoſe things, that afterward they would conſecrate to the Lord. The very ſame order was taken by the Apoſtles, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.12. On the Lords day there ſhould be Collection for the Poor; this was adjudged the proper day for Alms, and Charitable Diſtributions. When thou art re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned home ponder a while that which thou haſt heard, read or preached. Hide the Seeds of Gods Word in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urrows of thy Heart, that Satan ſteal it not away; uſe ſobriety of Meat and Drink, and careful temperance this day above all other times, that the Body may be ſtrengthned, and better diſpoſed to do the duties of Godlineſs. When thou art entred upon any diſcourſe with thy Neighbour, let it be concerning what was delivered that day, or diſcourſe about ſome other points of wholeſome Doctrine tending to Edification. In the afternoon return to Church and there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have thy ſelf at the Evening ſervice as is already preſcribed.</p>
            <p>After this is ended, and thou art come home, confer with thy Family, and ſee how they profit, read ſome part of the holy Scripture, joyn in prayers, and praiſe to Almighty God for the benefit of that days favour, and when thou art wearied with pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and reading and preaching is ceaſed, ſpend the remainder of the day in meditation; this is to continue the whole day, and ſtill findeth matter to work upon. Meditate on the Judgments of God, how many Families, who formerly wallowed in eaſe and plenty, are now reduccd to Beggary and Want. Meditate on the mercies of God; how we have been as Firebrands, ſnatched and reſcued out of the Fire, delivered from the burthen of Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny and Popery by the over ruling hand of Providence; Let us I ſay meditate on theſe Judgments and Mercies whether they
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152230:10"/>extend to our own Perſons, or come on our Fathers Houſe, or the place wherein we live, or the Church round about us: There are none of theſe but afford us a ſubject of meditation. Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate alſo on the Creatures of God, from the Leſs to the Greater; You may be ſupplyed with fit objects of your meditation: <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> in all his Glory was never arrayed like ſome of them, and they never were ungrateful to their maker, and if they be thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, how much more are we bound to him.</p>
            <p>If any Neighbour be ſick, or in any heavineſs, go to viſit him. If any be fallen at variance, help to reconcile them; <hi>Bleſſed are the Peacemakers for they ſhall be called the Children of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the time of reſt approacheth, deſire God to forgive thy defects in his ſervice, and to grant thee a quiet repoſe and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable refreſhment this night, that being raiſed to the comfort of the next morning thou mayeſt return, refreſhed and ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to thy wonted Labour, and dedicate both it and the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of thy days to Gods ſervice and honour.</p>
            <closer>Laus Deo Amen</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
